Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is כ"ז. Chaf-Zayin. We
pick up on the bottom of כ"ו עמוד ב' Chaf-Vav Amud-Bet where
the line starts with the word בעי מיניה—actually Boi minei the line
starts with the word יהודה. Yehuda. It is eight lines from the
bottom. בעי מיניה. Boi minei. We're talking about the idea that a
שליה shilya is assumed to have in it a fetus and therefore
the woman is טמאה לידה tmeiah leida and if it's in a
house then the house has the impurity of a corpse because there's
assumed to be a fetus that has dissolved. And the גמרא's's Gemara
discussion had been okay that's if all you have is a placenta.
Let's say you have a fetus and a placenta. Is the placenta
another fetus or is it connected to the current one? And the
תניא Tanya says well if the fetus is born as a נפל
nefel then the first one then the placenta within three days is
considered connected; more than that you have to be concerned it's another
fetus, another person. But if the first child is born as a
live birth then if this were another fetus it would have come
out right away. So if the first one is a live birth
and therefore the next thing is a placenta even if it comes
out a long time afterward we are saying that that could not
be another fetus, it is connected. And the last statement that we
had made was that which was told over in the name of
the students of רב Rav that only if this fetus is something
that would have been viable had it come to term then do
we assume
that the שליה shilya is connected to it. But if it was
a fetus that would not have been viable then this placenta might
be independent. So again this is a series of questions related to
the idea that with the placenta comes a fetus but if you
see a fetus can you connect it to this placenta or not?
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: בעי מיניה—about Boi minei
again eight lines from the bottom on כ"ו עמוד ב'—בעי מיניה רב
יוסי בן שאול Rav Yose ben Shaul מרבי. So רב Rav, יוסי
בן שאול asked רבי: Rebbi: המפלת דמות
עורב—let's Hamapelet demut oreiv say it looks like—so Rivka point it out
that we're back to the animal
appearances—so let's say the fetus looks like a raven. ושלייה v'shilya and
a placenta מהו. mahu.
So we had said that we don't attribute the placenta to be
connected to a fetus as we just said that it was not
going to become viable. What about if this other category of fetuses
which don't cause טומאת לידה tumat leida which is not—which is a
fetus that is—that does not you know that has this other type
of an appearance, does not have a human appearance? Would we assume
that the placenta is connected to it
or we would assume that the placenta is independent? And again it's
a question of do we give it you know how do we
consider that there's another fetus here for the relevant הלכה? halacha? אמר
ליה: Amar lei: אין תולין
אלא בדבר שיש במינו שליה.
Ein
tolin
ela bedavar sheyesh bemino shilya. So
it's only—you can only say the placenta's connected if this type of
a thing if it looks like a raven—and this again goes to
the point that maybe it's not just appearances, maybe the גמרא Gemara
to some degree thinks this is what it is, it's always that
ambiguity—it's only if this thing that it looks like has placentas with
it. So since mammals have placentas but birds do not and since
this fetus looks like a raven this placenta cannot obviously be connected
to this fetus. So here clearly at least it sounds like the
גמרא's's Gemara assuming that appearances indicate some essence of what this thing
is and therefore the placenta cannot be connected to this. So the
גמרא Gemara says: קשורה בו
מהו—let's Keshurah bo mahu say similar to what Mike was saying, let's
say it's really like it's intertwined, it's physically connected or intertwined, then
it clearly seems all the evidence is that it is part of
it. So what would you say then? אמר ליה: Amar lei: he
said to him דבר שאינו שאלת—for Davar she'eino she'altah once the גמרא
Gemara says eh that never happens. So that—I refuse to answer that
question. That will never happen. So he assumed that maybe because of
his assumption that if it looks like a raven there can't be
a placenta he refused to assume the possibility that there actually would
have been a placenta which would mean intertwined with it. איתיביה Eitvei
ask you on this: המפלת מין בהמה חיה ועוף—so Hamapelet min behemah
chayah va'of
this is a ברייתא braita that if somebody gives—if a woman—or excuse
me is this a woman or this is—might be an animal? Because
it's from—yeah I think it might be an
animal. המפלת—right Hamapelet right I'm sorry I take that back. I'm sorry
I'm sorry I take it back. It is a woman. A woman
miscarries something that looks like a בהמה—looks behemah like I know מין.
min.
All right you're right. Fine okay fine. A woman who miscarries a
type of—thank you—a type of animal or bird ושלייה
עמהן—with v'shilya imahen a placenta. בזמן שהשלייה קשורה עמהן Bizman she-hashilya keshurah
imahen
if the placenta is intertwined with them אין חוששין לולד אחר. ein
chosheshin levlad acher. There's no concern that this is a separate fetus
and a separate child; no it's all connected, it's all one. So
whatever status you give the fetus if you consider it to not
be a childbirth because of the appearance then the placenta doesn't matter.
But the placenta is not treated separately for possibility of another birth.
אין השלייה קשורה עמהן Ein hashilya keshurah imahen
if however the placenta is not connected then
חוששין לולד אחר chosheshin levlad acher then that is— Nevertheless, the placenta
indicates another fetus and therefore you have to be concerned for it.
So he says you see that it is possible that it's connected,
and even though in a case like this based on what's you
know the nature of the fetus, even if we would normally say
we're not concerned, when it's connected I mean excuse me we won't
make assume the the placenta's connected to it, when it's physically connected
we assume it's all one, we don't assume it's a second fetus.
So you see A, it happens and B, it has a relevance
in הלכה. halacha. So the same way here it's true about בהמה
חיה ועוף, behema chaya v'of, your example of a raven was essentially
a subset of that, right? So he says, now the ברייתא braita
finishes, let's take a look. אם חוששין לולד אחר, Im choshshin l'velad
acher, אם אין שליא קשורה עמהן חוששין לולד אחר. im ein shilya
keshura imahen choshshin l'velad acher. הרי אני מטיל עליהם חומר שני ולדות.
Harei ani matil aleihem chomer shenei vladot. So if you're concerned that
there are two, that there's A, number one the fetus you're seeing
and number two the placenta which is not connected which indicates a
second fetus, so what does it mean to be concerned about two
births? So הרי אני מטיל עליהם חומר שני ולדות harei ani matil
aleihem chomer shenei vladot that I'm concerned that it is two births.
Now what is the relevance of it being two births? Well, if
you assume that like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that a fetus that
looks like a בהמה חיה או עוף behema chaya o of is
considered a childbirth and has טומאת לידה, tumat leida, so by considering
the placenta a second one, it leads to the idea that well,
the first one maybe you would've identified as male because of the
placenta and you're assuming it independent you're going to be strict that
maybe it's female and therefore it leads to different parameters of טומאה
וטהרה, tuma v'tahara, or like the גמרא Gemara said before, one is
born on one day and the next is born on the next
day, it comes out on the next day, so that you know
makes a difference by considering to be another case of birth in
terms of the period of the טומאת לידה. tumat leida. According to
the חכמים Chachamim that something that an fetus that appears like בהמה
חיה ועוף behema chaya v'of does not have טומאת לידה, tumat leida,
so then really being strict for the placenta, it's not you're strict
for two births, it's like the first one doesn't have halakhic status
and you're really strict for the fact that the placenta itself might
be its independent birth and make this woman have the טומאה, tuma,
have the impurity of childbirth. Okay so now so that's the basic
point though when it's not physically connected we assume it's independent, as
opposed to before when it's a normal birth we assume that the
placenta that comes out three days later ten days later is always
connected. Here when the fetus looks this unusual way or literally is
this unusual thing, then we assume if unless the placenta is directly
physically connected it is not it is not part it is a
different type of a birth. Okay,
one minute, fine. So now it goes on and says like this.
שאני אומר She'ani omer because I say when it's not connected and
again it's this unusual birth that I do not assume that they
that it's I assume it's independent and therefore what happens? How come
you have one birth without a placenta, another placenta without a birth?
Doesn't it most make most sense to assume the puzzle pieces go
together even if they're not physically connected? No, once they're not physically
connected I say שמא נימוח שפיר של שליא, Shema nimuach shapir shel
shilya,
maybe the fetus of the of the of the placenta dissolved and
therefore you're getting a placenta without its fetus, the fetus has dissolved,
but it's really an independent birth, ונימוח שליא של שפיר v'nimuach shilya
shel shapir and the one
that is the fetus that looks this unusual way that its placenta
dissolved and therefore it is true of one placenta one fetus, you're
both inclined to say they go together, but because they're not physically
connected and because it looks unusual fetus it has it's in this
other category, therefore we have to be concerned they are not the
same. So anyway what do you see? You see that even when
it has this un this look, this animal-like look, we say that
if it's connected we assume it's one. תיובתא. Tyuvta. So that is
a contradiction to the assertion that being connected A doesn't happen and
B doesn't matter. Here we see it does happen and it does
matter. Okay, so now we've dealt with that case. We've dealt with
a case with a birth of a miscarriage, of when the placenta
is connected, a live birth when the placenta is connected, which we
said always, a birth of an animal of of animal you see
that, a birth of when the the fetus is not going to
be was not on the path of being viable, that we don't
say the placenta is connected, and a birth of a fetus when
it has these appearances, these animal appearances, and there we say it
only if it is physically connected do we attribute the placenta to
it. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבה בר שמואל אמר
רב חסדא אמר שמואל, Amar Rabba bar Shmuel amar Rav Chisda amar
Shmuel, מעשה, ma'aseh, there was a story, ותלתה השליא בולד עשרה ימים,
v'taltah hashilya b'velad asara yamim, that they said that the placenta was
connected to the fetus, not physically meaning it
was one birth with the fetus even ten days later. This presumably
would be a of gone back to our previous discussion a case
where it was a live birth and therefore even if the placenta
comes as a ברייתא braita says, if it was a live birth
if there was a second fetus it would've come right afterwards, so
if therefore if there's a placenta it can come ten days, a
hundred days later, we're not going to say, well a hundred days
might not be then it might be an actual new birth but
anyway, but we're not going to say that it was it was
a second fetus, we are going to say that it's always connected
to the first. Because of live birth. Okay, so he said even
ten days later. ולא אמרו *Velo amru* תולין *tulin* אלא בשיליא הבאה
אחר הולד *ela beshilya habaa achar havlad*. Now all of this is
only when the placenta follows the fetus. If first came out the
placenta and then the fetus, then we would be have to be
concerned and it seems like even literally during the same birth we
would have to be concerned that that was an independent, and I
guess assume physically not connected, but if preceded it then we would
have to be concerned that that was an independent fetus with all
the relevant הלכות halachot, *halachot* that was in there and that was
dissolved. By the way, again we don't have Sally here, but does
I assume that's very rare that that happens, that there's reason it's
called the afterbirth. But I don't know, but anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says if it happens, presumably because it's so rare, we
assume it's its own fetus and not connected.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Amar Rabba bar bar Chana
amar Rabbi Yochanan*, so says רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar bar
Chana* in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, מעשה
ותולין של שיליא בולד עד כ"ג ימים *maaseh vetolin shel shilya bavlad
ad chaf gimel yamim*. There's a case where we said that again,
we had before ten days, now we're saying a case twenty-three days
later. We still we did not assume that it was an independent
fetus since there was a presumably a live birth, the placenta that
came afterwards was part of that even twenty-three days later. אמר ליה
רב Rav, יוסף עד כ"ד אמרת לן *Amar lei Rav Yosef ad
chaf daled amart lan*. So so רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* said, "Oh,
you told us when you told it over twenty-three, not twenty-four." Alright.
אמר רב אחא *Amar Rav Acha* the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't do
anything with that. אמר רב אחא בריה דרב אבירא אמר רבי Rabbi
יצחק *Amar Rav Acha brei deRav Avira amar Rabbi Yitzchak*, so now
starting in the name of רבי Rabbi יצחק *Rabbi Yitzchak*, מעשה ונשתהא
ולד אחר חבירו ל"ג יום *maaseh venishtaha vlad achar chaveiro lamed gimel
yom*. Now we're not talking about a a placenta, we're talking about
an actual second birth.
Here we have so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
had a whole case about רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya *Rabbi Chiya* and
whatever, we'll take a we'll see anyway. Thirty-three days. Now there's a
little problem because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said before that when they're
live births they don't they come out right afterwards. So we'll take
a look. Thirty-three days. So if if the fetus dies inside the
mother,
it's poison in the mother's life and you have to get it
abort
it,
right? And a woman wouldn't really survive carrying around a dead fetus
because it poisons her.
Right, we don't have a dead fetus, we have we have carrying
around an afterbirth, and this case is it's
afterbirth
and then didn't say and then another?
Another what we've had so far is a fetus being born or
miscarried and then an afterbirth. And then now we've had a case
about a child being born and then the twin born thirty-three days
later.
And if it's live birth?
Yeah, it's assuming live. It's assuming live.
Because that's not possible, it can't happen.
Right, right, I hear you. Right, because if it's around right, it's
true. If there's a dead child of a fetus, it'll poison. Right,
but so far we haven't had that well, we have had, I
guess when it says that we're concerned that if it comes more
than a certain amount of days after it's an independent fetus. So
what you're saying is in the scenario that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
discusses, that there's a let's say a miscarriage and then a few
days later another a a placenta comes out, and the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says well we're concerned that's another fetus. Your point is if
that were really another fetus dissolved in that placenta, your point is
if that were really true then it would be risking the life
of the mother, wouldn't survive. That's an interesting, yeah, that's a good
point.
If it's dissolved, would it still be poison?
I don't know what that means.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, he's using the
word. I know, well that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming.
I don't know how much what the exact medical reality is to
all this.
A birth with nothing.
Right, right, and they're right, and they're speculating in terms of what
is it. Okay, yeah, no that's forget it, moving on. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר ליה רב יוסף *Amar
lei Rav Yosef*, okay fine, we did it. Okay, so thirty-three. Thirty-three
days. Now that's a little funny because before we said it doesn't
come it comes right afterwards, and now we're saying thirty-three days. Anyway,
אמר ליה רב יוסף ל"ד אמרת לן *Amar lei Rav Yosef lamed
daled amart lan*. Why, you told us it wasn't thirty-three, it was
thirty-four. Fine. Now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* wants to figure out how this could happen. Not because of
what we said before that if there's a second child it comes
right afterwards, but because of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s assumption that babies
born in their eighth month don't survive. And since it said that
there were two children, now why didn't just fine, one didn't survive,
but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* somehow the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming
because it said ולד אחר חבירו *vlad achar chaveiro* that without any
qualification it sounds like we're talking about a live and a viable
and a viable birth, one minute. So it wants to understand how
you can have two viable births if according to the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara*'s assumption only babies in their seventh month and in their ninth
month plus one minute are born. So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, הניחא למאן דאמר יולדת לתשעה
יולדת למקוטעין *Hani-cha leman deamar yoledes letisha yoledes lekitain*. According to the
approach that a woman who gives birth in her ninth month can
give birth to a viable child even if it's a partial month,
meaning anytime in the ninth month, not only at the end of
nine months. There's an opinion in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that to
give birth to a viable child in the ninth month it would
have to be at at the completion of nine months. Anytime even
a week or two weeks premature, anytime in the ninth month would
not be viable. So if you say, but if you disagree with
that and say anytime within the ninth month it's viable, then it's
easy. משכחת לה אחד נגמרה צורתו לסוף שבעה *mishkachat lah echad nigmera
tzurato lesof shiva*. The first it's twins the first one came out
at the end of seven months, like towards the end of the
seventh month. And then thirty-three or thirty-four days later you're in the
middle of the ninth month. ואחד נגמרה צורתו לתחילת תשעה *ve-echad nigmera
tzurato letchilat tisha* and the other one it was finished being formed
and it came out in the beginning of the ninth month, so
you have two live births. אלא למאן דאמר יולדת לתשעה אינה יולדת
מקוטעין, but according to the approach that a woman who gives birth
in the ninth month, it's only a live or not live viable
birth if it's at the end of the ninth month, מאי איכא
למימר, mai ika lemeimar, what can you say? If so, if baby
number two was born in month seven, the baby number one was
born in month seven, baby number two, how could it be born
in... if baby number one was born somewhere in month seven, and
baby number two was born, it's 33 days later, it had to
be born somewhere in
month nine, but it couldn't be born after nine months, right? Because
if baby number one was born literally at the last... what?
Why couldn't it be nine and ten months?
Why couldn't it have been born in full
term nine, and then the other one came out 33 days later
after the tenth month?
Well, yeah, I mean, that's what I didn't get either because if
it was, if one was born literally at the last day of
the seventh month and then you're 33 days later, wait, no, because
then you're at the beginning of the ninth... I understand, then you're
at the beginning of the ninth month.
Oh, seven and nine? Or nine and ten?
Oh, I don't think the גמרא Gemara thought that was possible.
I don't know, I don't know. Anyway, so this is what the
גמרא Gemara says. If the first one was born in month seven,
then the other one could have been born either in month eight
or in month nine because if you have 33 days you could
depending on where it was in month seven. But if it was
born, but there's no way that it could have been born in
month seven and the other at the after a full nine, and
therefore how do you have the second one as a viable birth?
And if the first one was in month nine, then as Michael
said, you would have had the second one in month ten, which
the גמרא Gemara, does not want to consider the possibility. That would
have been at... after ten full months. Anyway, all right. So now
the גמרא says like this, somebody should have given... okay, let's go
on. Anyway, so the גמרא says like this, so מאי איכא למימר,
mai ika lemeimar, so the גמרא says איפוך שמעתתא. ipuch shmateta. All
right, reverse it. When we said 33 and 23, ל"ג לשליא lamed
gimel leshilya
we got it mixed up. 33 was when the... when the placenta
came out 33 days later, that was the first story about the
placenta coming out later, that was 33. כ"ג לולד, kaf gimel levlad,
the fetus coming out later, that was 23. So how could it
work? Still, if you have to be at the end of a
full nine months, how do you get two with a separation of
23? Because very ironically, the גמרא assumes that even if a ninth
month baby has to be born after the full ninth month, a
seventh month baby can be born anytime in the seventh month. Very
funny that the גמרא thinks that there's greater viability of a baby
born anytime in the seventh month than born anytime of the eighth,
anytime in the ninth month until it's after a full nine. But
given the גמרא thinks that, then you could have two babies born
in the seventh month separated by 23 days, both being viable. So
that's how it explains it. Anyway, again, what's a little bit strange
about this is that this argues with what the גמרא said before,
which is... which is that if they're live births, they will come
right after one another. Here you have two cases of live births
that are actually separate, so that actually came at a good distance
from one another. Again, I'm sure if Charlie was here, somebody could
find on the World Book of World Records, Guinness Book of World
Records how long separated could two twins be in delivery? Didn't he
look it up once and it was 80 days? It was 80
days? Really?
Yeah, but that was... that was some sort of weird thing.
Well, no kidding!
Right. So I mean, so anyway, so I guess this... yeah, anyway,
these types of things under rare circumstances could happen. So now the
גמרא says, אמר אבדימי בר אבא רב אדא אמר רב מנחם איש
כפר שארים, amar avdimi bar abba rav adda amar rav menachem ish
kfar sharim, and some say, ואמרי לה בי שארים, ve'amri lah bei
sharim, either from the village of שארים Sharim or the house of
שארים, Sharim, מעשה ונשתהתה אחר חברתה ג' חדשים, maaseh venishtaata achar chavartah
gimel chadashim, there you go, so three months separated. Okay, now, how
would that work in terms of this idea? Well, let's see. If
one was born at the beginning of the seven, and you have
seven, eight, and one was born after nine, then you could get
it, right? Beginning of the seven and after nine. והריהם יושבים לפנינו
בבית המדרש, ve'hareihem yoshvim lefanenu beveit hamidrash, and they're right here in
the ישיבה, yeshiva, two live babies, so ברוך השם. baruch hashem. ומאן
נינהו, uman ninhu, who are they? So this is probably what Michael
was referring to, יהודה וחזקיה בני רבי חייא, yehuda vechizkiya bnei rabbi
chiya, the sons of רבי rebbe. חייא, Chiya, יהודה Yehuda and חזקיה,
Chizkiya, were twins, but with this type of three month separation. At
least that's what the גמרא understood. And therefore, it actually happened. Okay,
so the גמרא says, והא אמר מר אין אשה מתעברת וחוזרת ומתעברת,
ve'ha amar mar ein ishah mita'beret vechozeret umitaberet, so one minute, says
the גמרא, but it assumes that this would have only happened if
she would have gotten pregnant later, it would assume that it was
somehow identical twins or somehow during
the same act of conception. So how could this be? Like it
sounds like okay, after רבי rebbe חייא's Chiya wife conceived one, then
three months later she conceived the other, but that doesn't happen. Once
a woman is pregnant she doesn't conceive again until she gives birth.
אמר אביי טיפה אחת היתה ונחלקה לשנים, amar abaye tipa achat hayta
venichalka lishnayim, right, it was one drop of semen and it divided
into two. If they knew eggs, they would have said the egg
split. I wonder if there's any basis in the גמרא for assuming
that these were identical twins or not. But it really doesn't matter
if it was one drop of semen or not. What it means
is, fine, it was all the same night that she conceived both
of her sons.
אחד נגמר צורתו בתחילה ואחד בסוף. echad nigmar tzurato betchila ve'echad besof.
They were born at different times. They were both conceived at the
same time. One was born at the beginning of seven and the
other was born at the end of nine. So that is a
nice little discussion here about this question about when do you
assume... And here the Gemara assumes that you could actually have two
live births coming at different times. Now the Gemara continues. שליה בבית
הבית טמא. shellia b'vayis habayis tamei. So that was about the status
of the mother. Is she טמאה לידה? tme'ah leidah?
Do we assume childbirth? But now, how about the status of this
שליה shellia itself? If we're assuming there's a dead fetus dissolved inside
of it, then that has the טומאה tumah of a מת, meis,
of a corpse, and everything in the house is טמא, tamei, which
is what the חכמים Chakhamim say. And Rabbi Yose disagrees. Rabbi Yose
says, no, it dissolved before coming out. So we'll see what the
Gemara does with that. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, we taught: שליה בבית
הבית טמא. shellia b'vayis habayis tamei. So here's a ברייתא, baraita, says:
לא שהשליה ולד אלא שאין שליה שאין ולד עמה דברי רבי מאיר.
lo she-hashilya velad ella she-ein shilya she-ein velad immah divrei Rabbi Meir.
Not that the placenta is a fetus, but that there would not
be a placenta without a fetus with it, so there's some dissolved
fetus in it, and therefore it's a corpse, it's an infant corpse,
and everything in the house is טמא. tamei. That's what Rabbi Meir
says. Rabbi Yose, Rabbi Yehuda, and Rabbi Shimon, however, these three colleagues
of his, Rabbi Yose, Rabbi Yehuda, and Rabbi Shimon, מטהרין. m'taharin. They
all say the house is טהור. tahor. אמרו לו לרבי מאיר, Amru
lo l'Rabbi Meir, they said to Rabbi Meir: אי אתה מודה שאם
הוציאוהו בספל לבית החיצון שהוא טהור? iy at modeh she-im hotzi'uhu be-sefel
le-veit ha-chitzon she-hu tahor? Would you not agree that if they took
this שליה shellia in some type of a like, you know, vessel,
if they took it into the outer chamber, that the outer chamber
would be טהור? tahor? That if you move it to a different
room, we would not be concerned about a fetus? Now, I don't
know why they knew he agreed to that, maybe he didn't,
but he said אבל. aval. אמרו לו אבל, amla'n aval, which again
as we know is from other ברייתות, baraitos, you know, where we've
had
interestingly in recent, you know, this מסכת, masekhet, we've had a couple
of cases of like exchanges, you know, more direct exchanges. Anyway, he
said then yes, I can see that point. ולמה? Valamah? Why?
לפי שאינו. Lefi she'eino. By the time you move it into a
second room, it will completely have dissolved and therefore it will no
longer cause טומאה. tumah. Ah, so if you say that, אמרו לו,
amru lo, they said to him: כשם שאינו בבית החיצון, keshem she'eino
b'veis hachitzon, the same way when you bring by the time if
you move it, the jostling around or whatever when you move it
to the other room, will cause it to dissolve and therefore not
have the טומאה, tumah, כך אינו בבית הפנימי, kach eino b'veis hapnimi,
that's true even in the inner chamber where it was where it
originally, you know,
was delivered. אמר להן, Amar lahen, he said back to them: אינו
דומה נימוק פעם אחת לנימוק שתי פעמים. eino domeh nimokh pa'am achas
le-nimokh shtei pe'amim. It's not similar dissolved once, dissolved twice, which means
yes, it's somewhat dissolved here but presumably has enough form and shape
that it's still considered to be present, whereas by the time if
you move it and the jostling, that'll cause it to completely dissolve
and not present. So it sounds at this stage that the debate
is either, in the Mishnah it sounded like the debate, everybody agreed,
well, in the Mishnah it sounded like the debate was when does
it dissolve? Did it dissolve before coming out of the woman's body
in the womb? Or did it dissolve after? Dissolved before, then it
didn't have the status, after when it came out when it had
not yet dissolved, then it had the status. Here it sounds like
the question of that before or after, meaning in the womb or
out of the womb, the question is right when it originally is
delivered, is it dissolved yet or not? But everybody agrees that when
it does dissolve, according to this version, it is not the טומאה,
tumah, and the only question is has it dissolved fully or not?
Okay, and that's what it sounds like until now, that it's more
about a factual question about at what stage has it dissolved or
dissolved fully. But the Gemara is going to turn it more into
somewhat of a halakhic debate rather than of a factual debate.
Once it's fully dissolved, no matter what it is, it's not like
other טומאות. tumas. If you go over a very old gravesite...
no, well, no, first of all, you still have bones or whatever.
So there are certain ways we'll get to that in a minute
about certain things like full things that more like it becomes dust
and not dust, but whatever, we'll get to that in a minute.
Here we're talking about like liquid types of dissolved, it's different because
it's an unformed fetus. But the difference is here, right, that is
a question, meaning in the Mishnah as I said, it sounds like,
oh, if it was born, you know, in its form and dissolved
later, it doesn't matter, it still retains its status. That's the implication
of the Mishnah. The only question was, was it born with its
form? Here it sounds like even if it was born with its
form, once it has dissolved, it loses its status. And then the
quest, the only question is when has it dissolved? But let's take
a look, because the Gemara is not, is not by any means
done. So let's take a look.
יתיב רב פפא אחוריה דרב ביבי קמיה דרב המנונא. Yasiv Rav Pappa
achorei d'Rav Bibi k-amei d'Rav Hamnuna. So Rav Pappa was sitting behind
Rav Bibi in front of Rav Hamnuna, so Rav Hamnuna was giving
the שיעור shiur and Rav Pappa was in the second row of
the class. ויתיב וקאמר, V'yasiv v'kamar, and he was sitting and saying:
מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Shimon? What is the reasoning
of Rabbi Shimon, meaning Rav Hamnuna was saying this. He was learning
this Mishnah, he was saying, what's the reason of Rabbi Shimon? And
he said: קסבר כל טומאה שנתערבה בה ממין אחר בטילה. kasavar kol
tumah she-nisarvah bah mi-min acher betailah. So he did not emphasize just
being dissolved, just being dissolved, it's all there, who cares if it's
dissolved or not? No, he said because there's other stuff mixed in,
in the embryonic sac there is all of these other liquids, and
therefore that somehow nullifies, we'll talk in a minute, does it mean
that you need a majority of the other liquids, is it normal
like laws of ביטול? bittul? But you know when you have a
majority of something else, it like negates the presence of the other
thing. But he said it's because of all the other liquids that
makes it like this thing is not here. So now, notice, it's
not a question did it dissolve or not? The question is what
is the halachic status when it's mixed up with other things? Does
that make it like it doesn't exist? So it's a halachic debate,
and that's what he says. אמר להו Amar lehu רב פפא, Rav
Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa said to them, היי hai you
know what? You mentioned רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but in the ברייתא
braita we have other תנאים tannaim said. So היינו נמי טעמא דרבי
יהודה ורבי יוסי. hayinu nami tama de-Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Yose. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose are there together with
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, so they also hold of the same idea.
So אחיכו עליה, achichu alei, they laughed at him. So we had
this a second time in two days where we had the אמוראים
amoraim sort of a little bit like, you know, not being as
much דרך ארץ derech eretz to one another as would have been
ideal. So they laughed at him. מאי שנא הכא, mai shena hach,
of course, what do you mean they're all said together? So he
gave the reason of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but of course they
all hold the same reason. Now what a silly thing to say.
Oh that's also their reason? It's obvious. פשיטא, peshita, of course. אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, said רב פפא, Rav Pappa, so רב
פפא Rav Pappa was the one that was laughed at: אפילו כי
אמילתא דבי איניש ולא נשכא מרביה. afillu ki amilta le-bei inish ve-lo
nishkamei rabbai. Even such a thing you should say, if you need
to make a point or you need to clarify a point and
you should not be silent in front of your רבי. rebbe, The
רבי said רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and he wanted to clarify that
it wasn't limited to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but also applied to
the other תנאים, tannaim, although they all three said the same thing.
Who knows? You know, maybe they had three different reasons. So even
if it's relatively obvious, you should say it and not be afraid
about being laughed at and not be afraid about being embarrassed, משום
שנאמר, mishum shene'emar, because the verse says: אם נבלת
בהתנשא. im nabalta be-hitnasei.
If you have, if you know, if you have made yourself despicable,
actually, not despicable, that's the wrong word here,
like a נבילה, neveila, like if you have made yourself like lowly
when it comes to learning תורה, Torah, בהתנשא, be-hitnasei, then it will
ultimately lead to you being raised up. If you make yourself lowly,
you will be raised up. אם זמות, im zamota, and if however
you have, you have, you know, you've been arrogant and silent,
then יד לפה, yad la-peh, in the end you will have your,
you know, hand to your mouth, which basically means like, I mean,
the phrase we're most familiar with is, you know, לא הביישן למד,
lo habayshan lamed, right? You know, and that what were you going
to say, Seth? Well, put your foot in your mouth. Yeah, I
don't know if that was his point, but his point was like,
don't be concerned about your honor, even if it's in front of
your רבי, even if you think it's relatively obvious, even if you
guys are going to laugh at me, don't be concerned about your
honor for the sake of clarifying תורה. Torah. In the end, you
will be elevated by the process. But if you're so concerned about
your honor and you don't want to say things and look stupid,
in the end you're going to be pulled down.
Okay, make something in it,
מבטלין אותו באיסור לכתחילה.
mevatlin oto be-issur le-chatchila. I don't know, but I'm not getting into
that. מבטלין mevatlin okay. Let's take a look.
No, everyone can go there, you know.
Yeah, yeah, I understand. ואזדא רבי שמעון לטעמיה. ve-azda Rabbi Shimon le-taimeih.
Now back to the basic issue about the fact that it's mixed
in with something else, we're gonna look at the parameters of what
that means mixed in with something else. ואזדא רבי שמעון לטעמיה דתניא
בברייתא: ve-azda Rabbi Shimon le-taimeih de-tanya be-braita: מלא תרוואד רקב. melo tarvad
rekav. Now there's a הלכה halacha that if a מת meis
decomposes and that's what רקב, rekav, again, I'm not exactly sure who
the word. Whatever, right sort of like the decomposition of a dead
body so it no longer has its form, it still causes טומאה
tumah if it is a מלא רקב, melo rekav, which is a
size of some type of a vessel. No, תרוואד רקב, tarvad rekav,
what? I'm sorry, רקב, rekav, right, רקב rekav is the decomposed, תרוואד
tarvad is some type of a like of a vessel. So therefore
a certain amount of this decomposed matter actually causes the טומאה tumah
of a מת. meis. But as we're going to see in a
minute, only under highly special circumstances where there's nothing else mixed in,
the מת meis was buried naked in a sort of in a
marble casket so there could be absolutely no other dust, no anything
mixed in. And then if you have this decomposed matter, then it
causes טומאה. tumah. But if there was something at the time when
it was decomposing mixed in, then it won't. So it means almost
never, this will never happen.
It has to be like the flesh, right, not just like the
bone or something.
No, the flesh and the bone. Okay, so probably not the blood.
But okay, so that's the הלכה. halacha. Now the question we're dealing
with is let's say you actually have this, which it'll almost be
impossible, and then something got mixed in afterwards, would it still cause
טומאה? tumah? So that you see the analogy to our case, you
have something that's the basis of טומאה tumah that something else got
mixed up into it afterwards. So let's take a look. מלא תרוואד
רקב שנפל לתוכו עפר כל שהוא, melo tarvad rekav shenafal le-tocho afar
kol shehu, the tiny little bit of dust fell into this container
of this, these ashes, of these not ashes, of this decomposed matter,
whatever the word is. טמא, tamei, it's still טמא. tamei. רבי שמעון
מטהר, Rabbi Shimon metaher, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's טהור. tahor.
מאי טעמיה דרבי שמעון, mai taimeih de-Rabbi Shimon, what's the reason? So
אמר רבא אשכחינהו לרבנן דבי רב דיתבי וקאמרי, amar Rava ashkichinu le-rabbanan
de-bei Rav di-basi ve-ka'amei, I found the rabbis of the ישיבה yeshiva
of רב, they were sitting and saying: אי אפשר שלא ירבו שתי
פרידות עפר על פרידה אחת של רקב וחצר ליה, ee efshar she-lo
yarbu shtei peridot afar al perida achat shel rekav ve-chatzeir lei,
that in somewhere in this mix there will be some section, although
even if the dust is like 1% of the mix, but if
you go to that tiny little place where the dust is, where
this external dirt is, in that little
section So in that little section there’ll be a majority of the
dust and it’ll negate a little part of the decomposed matter and
you won’t have enough of the minimum amount. Is that clear?
No. No?
And it would be different. Okay. But if you have a precise
amount and you have something external mixed in, in the location where
that external thing is, it is the majority and it negates a
little bit of the thing and it makes less than the amount.
Of course תוספות Tosafot says, but but here by the fetus you
don’t have an exact amount, you have a whole fetus, why should
this be a problem? So תוספות Tosafot says a very interesting point,
תוספות Tosafot says רש"י Rashi has a different approach, but תוספות’s Tosafot
approach says, he says look,
normally how do we say a מת meit causes טומאה? tumah? If
you’ve got a bone of a certain size or you’ve got flesh
of a certain size or you’ve got a limb, he says this
type of a thing which has none of its form, you can’t
call it the טומאה tumah of a bone, you can’t call it
the טומאה tumah of a flesh, you can’t call it the טומאה
tumah of a limb, because it has like none of that’s the
form of any of that. He says the only thing you could
call it is a טומאה tumah of a מת שלם, meit shaleim,
of an entire corpse. Okay, because you do have an—like the entire
corpse here, but you don’t have the flesh of it, you don’t
have the bone of it, but you have the entire corpse. But
that means it has to be present in its entirety. And therefore,
if the tiniest little part is missing, if you can say that
some of the other liquids negate even the tiniest part, you don’t
have the entire corpse.
It’s not missing, it’s just ביטול bitul or something.
It’s רוב rov that negates it. No, if if the other liquids
negate even a little piece of it, what halachically make it like
it’s not there, even a little piece, you don’t have the concept
of an entire corpse. Like so again, you know, take the case
by the way of dissolved. You know, the הלכה halacha normally is
you need let’s say a כזית kezayit of a flesh of a
corpse to cause טומאה tumah in a roof. Let’s say there was
a case of a miscarriage under forty days, excuse me, after forty
days, that the entire fetus was less than a כזית. kezayit. I
can’t imagine that’s the case, but let’s say it was. So הלכה
halacha is it still causes טומאה tumah in a under the roof.
Because even though it doesn’t fit the category of flesh to be
enough flesh, the idea of a whole corpse causes טומאה. tumah. So
תוספות Tosafot says that’s all you have here. You don’t have flesh,
you don’t have bones, all you have is a whole corpse. And
the little bit that becomes negated, then you don’t have a whole
thing and therefore it does not cause טומאה.
tumah. That also means that aside from mixing something in, even if
just a little bit was gone.
Correct, even a little bit was taken away, correct, correct.
What is
it? Non-temped inside the sac but in terms of a body. What’s
an entire corpse without any bones?
Right, right, it would never happen. The only relevance
of
saying a טומאה—right, tumah right, the only case of causing
of calling about a טומאה tumah of an entire corpse without having
the other categories is in a case like this. A case either
it’s a tiny fetus or inside the sac and dissolved so you
can’t say the other physical things are present, but at least you
can still have the idea of the entire corpse. So that was
the answer.
So ואמינא להו, ve'amina lehu, so he said, so רבא Rava said
I said back to these students of
רב, אדרבה, adaraba, what do you mean the opposite makes
sense! אי אפשר שלא ירבו שתי
פרידות רקב rekev, על פרידה—עמוד ב'—על פרידה אחת עפר וניבצו חיוריה. venivtzu
chivrei. He says since when when we do ביטול bitul do we
look at this sort of microscopic way and look at the exact
presence of you know of the tiny place where one thing is
more? We look at the whole thing! So anyway if you just
make it a little more macro, obviously there’s always going to be
more of the of the רקב, rekev. of the decomposed matter, than
there will be of dirt. And therefore the dirt will go away,
not the decomposed matter. There’ll actually be more, it’ll increase the amount,
not decrease the amount, because the dirt will be בטל batel to
the רקב. rekev So how can you say that thing? It can’t
be a tiny little bit makes a difference. Do we go by
רוב? rov? You look at the whole thing. So אלא אמר רבא,
ela amar Rava, so רבא Rava said היינו טעמא דרבי שמעון, hinu
taama deRabbi Shimon, I’ll tell you the reason of רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. We’re still in the case of the decomposed matter, we’re going
to make the analogy in a minute. סופו כתחילתו. sofo kitechilato. So
I already hinted this to you. The end, when external stuff gets
mixed in, follows the same laws at the beginning. This whole הלכה
halacha of רקב rekev. of decomposed matter of the corpse is a
very special case and only under extremely narrow circumstances, and there can’t
be any external matter at the beginning. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says the same way there can’t be external matter at the beginning,
which is a very special הלכה halacha here, right then there also
cannot be external matter at the end. מה תחילתו נעשה לו דבר
אחר גנגילון. ma techilato na’asa lo davar acher gangilon. The same at
the beginning some external thing becomes a גנגילון. gangilon. רש"י Rashi says
גנגילון gangilon means an opposition. But I looked at Jastrow, apparently it
comes from a Roman word singulum or something which means a—like a
belt. Because there’s actually a—a place where it says that if the—if
there was even a belt on the corpse and they dissolved with
the corpse, it prevents this law of רקב. rekev. So it’s sort
of symbolic of the idea of something external which prevents this law
from taking effect. So the same way at the beginning something external
prevents the law from taking
effect, אף סופו נעשה לו דבר אחר גנגילון. af sofo na’asa lo
davar acher gangilon. Even at the end some little external
thing prevents—you know, some—you know, undermines—prevents this law and therefore it does
not cause—it wouldn’t cause טומאה. tumah. מאי? mai? Where is this idea?
דתניא d'tanya. *detanya*, we're taught in a ברייתא braisa *Baraita*, איזהו מת
mes, שיש לו רקב rekev. *eizehu meit sheyesh lo rekeiv*? What is
a type of a corpse that has the law of decomposed matter
that even after it's decomposed it causes טומאה tuma *tumah*? ואיזהו מת
mes, שאין לו רקב *ve'eizu meit she'ein lo rekeiv*? And which is
one that does not? נקבר ערום בארון של שיש *nikvar arom bearon
shel shayish*, buried naked in a marble casket, או על גבי רצפה
של אבנים *o al gabi ritzpah shel abanim*, or left on a
stone floor, so it had nothing else on it, none of the
material of the thing it was in could have would have had
some decomposition, so it's only the decomposition of the מת mes. *meit*
and nothing else. זהו מת met. שיש לו רקב *zehu meit sheyesh
lo rekeiv*, that's a מת met *meit* that the decomposed matter is
considered to be a source of טומאה tuma, *tumah*. ואיזהו מת met?
שאין לו רקב *ve'eizu meit she'ein lo rekeiv*, which is one that
does not have this law? נקבר בכסותו *nikvar bikhsuto*, if it actually
had some clothes on it, shrouds, או בארון של עץ *o be'aron
shel eitz*, or if you did anything הלכה halacha. *halakhah*-ly, כהלכה *kehalakhah*,
then it's not going to have רקב *rekeiv*. It was in a
wooden casket because then the wood would also be part
of the מת met, *meit* from touching the bone?
Yeah, just if it's all decomposed. Or if the wood... by the
way, bones, right, even hundreds of years later the bones are still
there, so this must have been just like the flesh has decomposed,
right? I mean what happens when they open up those old caskets
and they find, if it's really, really old they find bones, they
also find I assume like what, decomposed flesh? Or has it all
been consumed by maggots? It's all been consumed by the maggots and
whatever. Just bones. I see.
But they would come
in the time of the תנ"ך *Tanakh* and then rebury the bones.
Right, rebury the bones after a year. Right, after a year. So
I'm just trying to figure out where is this רקב *rekeiv* coming
from because the bones don't become רקב *rekeiv*, the flesh probably gets
completely eaten away by maggots so you probably don't even have the
flesh. I mean, if you didn't have maggots, if you didn't have
maggots, like what happens when they do in mausoleums? I don't know,
where it's actually not in the ground, it's protected, sealed. Mummies, right.
I guess that's true, that's a good point. So when you undo
the mummy wrapping, then it's all like it... that probably is like
that decomposed stuff.
Yeah, I just know some research being done on DNA of these
bodies, so where is DNA coming from?
Right, there is some organic matter left is what you're saying. Right.
In the bone. In the bone.
In the bone. Oh, okay.
But this is the case you just dug it up early, you
didn't wait a year.
I know, but I'm saying of all the flesh that's being eaten
is being destroyed by the maggots and not that it's left to
decompose there, where is this רקב *rekeiv*? So that's part of the
reason I imagine why we also need it to be in this
marble casket is to prevent the maggots from getting in, although the
גמרא *Gemara*, it's saying here that you need it in order because
any external thing would have prevented these laws. Okay. זהו מת meys
ש... *zehu
meit she...* okay, where were we? או בארון של עץ *o be'aron
shel eitz*, או על גבי רצפה של לבנים *o al gabi ritzpah
shel leveinim*, if it's not on stone floor but if it's on
like a brick floor, so there's more like matter there that will
decompose. זהו מת שאין לו רקב *zehu meit she'ein lo rekeiv*. That
is one that does not have this law of decomposed matter because
there's something external that's there while it is decomposing, that decomposes with
it. ולא אמרו רקב אלא למת בלבד *velo amru rekeiv ela lemeit
bilvad*. And they only said this by a corpse. What do you
mean by a corpse? למעוטי הרוג דלא *lim'utei harug delo*, meaning if
it's a murder victim, no. Why should it matter? רש"י *Rashi* says
because you don't have it all there because you don't have the
blood. Not all the blood is there. Now תוספות *Tosafot* points out
of course the blood is not what is decomposing here for the
law of רקב *rekeiv*, but nevertheless the הלכה halacha *halakhah* requires that
the מת *meit* be buried complete. In another one of the criteria.
It can't be anything external and it has to be buried what?
Yes, הלכה halacha למשה מסיני *halakhah lemoshe misinai*. Okay, anyway so you
see that it has to be completely free of external things and
therefore רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* would say here too when
the external thing gets mixed up later, at least by this special
law of רקב *rekeiv*, it is not a problem. Of course what
that has to do with our case of a fetus we don't
know yet. גופא *gufa*, let's take a look at what we just
said. מלא תרווד רקב שנפל לתוך עפר כל שהוא טמא tamei. *melo
tod rekeiv shenafal letoch afar kol shehu tamei*. So if you have
this fill container or whatever of this רקב *rekeiv*, of this decomposed
matter that a little bit fell into it, it is טמא *tamei*,
a little dirt. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon מטהר *Rabbi Shimon metaher*. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says it's טהור tahor? *tahor*. מלא תרווד
רקב שנתפזר בבית *melo tod rekeiv shenitpazer babayit*. Now let's say you
have this whole thing and it wasn't all in one container, it
was the right amount but it was spread throughout the house. הבית
טמא *habayit tamei*. So okay, house is טמא *tamei*. Doesn't all have
to be in the same place. It's all under the same roof,
it's still a problem. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon מטהר *Rabbi Shimon metaher*.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says it's טהור tahor? *tahor*. וצריכא
*utrichah*, you need to tell us both cases. דאי אשמעינן קמייתא *di'ashmian
kama'ita*. Now notice by the way the second case there's no dirt,
right? It's just spread throughout the house. Do you understand? There are
two different debates. One is you have it all in one place
and there's some external matter mixed in, some dirt. The other case
is only the thing itself but it's spread throughout the house. Now
you could say spread throughout the house also
has external stuff mixed into it, but maybe that's also a separate
consideration. Maybe it's spread throughout the house and it's all on a
glass floor or something. I don't know. So let's take a look.
וצריכא *utrichah*, you need both cases. דאי אשמעינן קמייתא *di'ashmian kama'ita*, if
you just told me the first one, I would have said בהא
דאמרי רבנן *beha de'amri rabbanan*. That's why the רבנן *rabbanan* say it's
טמא *tamei* when it's all together and there's some dirt mixed in,
משום דמיכנף *mishum denikhnaf*, because it's all gathered together so it all
has the... And it's טמא *Tamei*, that's the הלכה halacha *Halacha*. אבל
נתפזר *Aval nitpazer*, but if it's scattered throughout the house, אימא מודו
ליה לרבי שמעון *Eima modu lei l'rabbi shimon*, maybe they agree to
Rabbi Shimon. Why should they agree if it's scattered throughout the house?
דאין מאהיל בחוזר ומאהיל *D'ein ma'ahil bechozer u'ma'ahil*, מאהיל *Ma'ahil*. Not because
there's something external which changes the status mixed into it, but because
it's like two acts of being an אהל *Ohel*, meaning if I
have this dust scattered throughout the house, it's not like there's an
amount here that there's a roof over. Here the roof is over
a little bit, over here the roof is over a little bit,
over there the roof is, now of course it seems to be
all the same roof, but nevertheless it's considered to be maybe that
it should be like separate mounds that don't combine. You know, I
mean, by a very loose analogy, the same way if you eat
a little bit, wait a half hour, eat a little bit more,
wait a half hour, eat another half of a כזית kezayit *Kezayit*,
right? It needs to happen within a certain context to say it's
all one process and it all is one event. So here too,
even if you have the right amount, but if it's spread throughout
the house, maybe that's not defined as like one unit or one
act of being a roof over it, maybe it's multiple ones and
that doesn't work. So it says no, it doesn't matter, it's all
in the same house, even if it's not all in one place,
it's all טמא *Tamei*. That's what the Rabbis say. אבל בהא *Aval
beha*, so wait, ואי אשמעינן בהא *Ve'ee ashmeinan beha*, if we had
just said the case about scattered throughout the house that רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* says it's טהור tahor? *Tahor*, I would have
said בהא אמר רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Beha amar Rabbi Shimon*. That's
where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says it has nothing to
do with external matter, it has to do with the reason of
דאין מאהיל בחוזר ומאהיל *D'ein ma'ahil bechozer u'ma'ahil*. It's not because there's
other stuff mixed in, it's just because if it's not all together,
then it's considered multiple different things or multiple different acts of being
a roof over it and it's not a roof over the minimum
amount. אבל בהא *Aval beha*, but if it's all in one place
and there's just some dirt mixed in, אימא מודו ליה לרבנן *Eima
modu lei l'rabbanan*, maybe he would agree. צריכא *Tzricha*, you need it.
So it seems like there are really two independent debates. One debate
is external matter mixed in and the other debate is the right
amount but spread out at a great distance. I mean, and that
could be a question even not with רקב *Rekev*. Let's say you
had a כזית kezayit *Kezayit* of of of flesh and it was
chopped up into tiny little pieces and spread throughout. Okay, but maybe
here it's even more because here it's just so thin and so
small it's harder to view it as one.
But it always has to be together though.
What? It has to be under the same roof. It is under
the same roof, but it's not together.
Same roof meaning in this, would this be the same roof, like
in this room in in the west part of the room and
east, yes. But if it was this room and then the other
room, then it wouldn't be?
Well, if they're connected by a similar door, then it is. I
mean, maybe that, you know, you could theoretically maybe want to distinguish,
maybe that's two roofs that are connected as opposed to one roof.
Anyway, but that's the question it's asking. And maybe is this the
same as if it were a divided piece of flesh or maybe
it's different. Anyway, but that's a separate consideration. That's a separate debate.
It's not the same as a debate of mixed something external mixed
up. So now it says like this, okay now. תניא אידך *Tanya
idach*, we taught another ברייתא braisa. *Braita*. מלא תרווד ועוד עפר בית
הקברות *Melo tarvad ve'od afar beit hakevarot*. Let's say you have not
directly from the coffin and from the decomposed מת *Met*, but you
actually take dirt from a cemetery and it is the minimum amount,
this מלא תרווד *Melo tarvad* with a little bit extra. So טמא
*Tamei*. That is טמא *Tamei*. Now that's strange that the חכמים chachamim,
*Chachamim* would say טמא *Tamei* because you would think, what is the
likelihood number one, since it's so impossible to get this רקב *Rekev*
anyway, it has to be in a marble without a naked and
so on. And number two is, a random amount from the cemetery
is only going to have a tiny amount of this רקב *Rekev*
in it. So the חכמים *Chachamim* nevertheless are very strict, it presumably
is a rabbinic extension, it's not really that we say that it
has the minimum amount in it, but the חכמים *Chachamim* say it's
טמא *Tamei*.
And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon מטהר *Rabbi Shimon metaher*, and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* says it's it's טהור tahor? *Tahor*. מאי טעמא
דרבנן *Mai ta'ama derabbanan*, what's the reason of the Rabbis? לפי שאי
אפשר למלא תרווד ועוד עפר בית הקברות *Lefi she'ee efshar lemelo tarvad
ve'od afar beit hakevarot*, it's impossible with if you have this minimum
amount plus of the dirt of a cemetery, שאין בו מלא תרווד
רקב *She'ein bo melo tarvad rekev*, that it doesn't have the full
amount of this decomposed part of the dead. Now again, that's a
little bizarre. What are you talking about? As I just said, first
of all the likelihood that you get this type of רקב *Rekev*
that matters is very tiny, and number and it should be anyway
deep deep down there in the grave, not just your normal amount
of dirt that you pick up. And number two, you know, the
proportion of that רקב *Rekev* to the amount of dirt in a
cemetery is also very tiny. So this really does seem to be
much more of a rabbinic extension and
not
really that this is really, and תוספות's *Tosafot's* explanation is one minute,
yeah, so תוספות *Tosafot* has a special case to try to make
it a little bit more understandable, one minute,
yeah, so
תוספות *Tosafot* tries to re-explain it of a special case that somebody,
you knew somebody was buried naked, you knew they were buried in
this type of a circum, whatever, a very special case that that
you know, that it makes it much more likely that it really
has the minimum amount. But anyway, this that is a little stranger
because that does not, it sounds like it's either rabbinic extension or
a very special case. Let's just go on. So now the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this. Now we have to go back. Now that
we've had this whole discussion about the about the רקב, about the
decomposed body. Fine, that's a special case because you need to have
it nothing external in the beginning, so סיפא דקתני seifa d'katani nothing
external at the end. What does that have to do with our
case of the fetus in the placenta? That's not that special הלכה.
halachic So why should why should it be dissolved matter in terms
of its status? And why should רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. say טהור?
So let's take a look. גמרא says like this: השתא
דאמרת hashta d'amarta טעמא דרבי שמעון משום סופו כתחילתו. taama d'Rabbi Shimon
mishum sofo k'tchilato. Now that you say that רבי שמעון's's reason is
that the end is like the beginning. Meaning the same way at
the beginning there are special הלכות, halachot there are special הלכות at
the end. גבי שליא מאי טעמא? gabei shilya mai taama? Why by
the case of the placenta does he say that it's טהור? That's
not the special הלכה of רקב. So what why why would say
it's טהור? And you can't say oh a little bit is less
than the שיעור, shiur, a little bit is בטל batel and it's
not a full מת, because we said before the opposite is true.
There's more you know the fetus negates the other liquid. So you
can't say you know so you have a full מת, it's dissolved.
Yes, there's some external matter, but why should it matter? So אמר
רבי יוחנן משום ביטול ברוב נהגו בה. amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum bitul
b'rov nahagu bah. We're going to have to assume that רבי שמעון
is assuming and all those that agree with him that the majority
of the of the mixture is not the fetus. That there's a
majority of other liquids there in the placental sac in the you
know in that that that is not the fetus. And that when
the fetus dissolves, the fetus is negated by a majority of others.
And that's our classic principle of ביטול ברוב. bitul b'rov. But until
now we were trying to say it's special הלכה but a little
external, but we said that's by רקב. Okay, it's a special הלכה
that a little bit is negated and then you don't have the
full מת. So why should a little bit be able to negate
it if the if the fetus is the majority? So now it's
said okay we'll have to assume the fetus isn't a majority and
therefore it loses its status. Okay. Yes.
What's the point of making this distinction between the fetus and the
placental sac as if they're two separate things? Right.
Are they I mean I don't understand that. What do you mean?
I mean the the fetus is growing in the you
know but that's very different than saying like a little bit of
dirt gets mixed into the decomposition of this corpse.
Right. I mean I mean they're organically the same but only the
fetus has the טומאת מת. tumas mes. So you have the fetus,
right, it's growing in the sac, it's filled with what type of
liquid? Is it water in there? What's in there?
Whatever. Anyway, it's in there. So it's true, it's all organically connected,
but only the fetus is the טומאת מת. tumas mes. So if
you assume this liquid is the majority of the content of what's
in that sac and then somehow the fetus has dissolved then you
have a big mixture here.
But they're inseparable. Like the fetus can't grow without the I mean
they're sort of in
I understand but that doesn't that doesn't make it yes doesn't give
it its status of a fetus. Right. Okay. So now the גמרא
says okay ואזדא
רבי יוחנן לטעמיה. v'azda Rabbi Yochanan l'taameih. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who
says that it's about רוב rov follows his reasoning. דאמר רבי יוחנן
רבי שמעון ורבי אלעזר בן יעקב אמרו דבר אחד. d'amar Rabbi Yochanan
Rabbi Shimon v'Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov amru davar echad. רבי שמעון and
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov are basically following saying
a similar idea. Now so which are these two תנאים? Tannaim? When
you say אמרו דבר אחד amru davar echad it usually means like
in different הלכה categories but following a similar approach. רבי שמעון הא
דאמרן. Rabbi Shimon ha d'amran. רבי שמעון what we said, that he
says that the you know that
there's no טומאת מת tumas mes here in this dissolved fetus because
as the way רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan understands it the majority of
the embryonic fluid you know negates it. And what about רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב? Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov? דתניא. We taught in a ברייתא
in בכורות Bechoros or דתנן d'tnan really a משנה. mishna. רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב אומר בהמה גסה ששפעה חררת דם. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov
omer behema gassa sheshaf’ah chararas dam. So let's say a large animal,
a cow, you know expelled a chunk of matter a chunk of
blood. הרי זו תקבר. harei zu tikaveir. So we're concerned that what
it really did was that this was a a miscarried fetus. And
if it's a miscarried fetus it would be a בכור. bechor. Okay.
So that would mean that the second we're assuming in the case
that it's the first birth. So the second child would not be
a בכור. bechor. So what do you do with this one? הרי
זו תקבר harei zu tikaveir bury it because if it was a
בכור bechor you can't derive benefit. So you bury it. ופטורה מן
הבכורה. u'ftura min ha'bechora. And from now on the animal is exempt
from בכורה bechora because we assume that this was the first one.
Okay. So what why is that relevant? ותני רבי חייא. v'sani Rabbi
Chiya. So רבי חייא then taught on this to explain this position.
אלא אינו מטמא לא במגע ולא במשא. ela eino metamei lo b'maga
v'lo b'massa. That the fetus that this thing that you just buried
is not does not have the טומאה tuma of a נבילה neveila
of an animal carcass. And if you touch it or carry it
you are not טמא. So it's not considered to really be the
animal in there. It's like so אמאי. amai. So גמרא says ומאחר
שאינו מטמא לא במגע ולא במשא מאי תקבר. u'meiachar she'eino metamei lo
b'maga v'lo b'massa mai tikaveir. So this is still part of the
ברייתא. So if it does not cause טומאה, tuma so if there's
no טומאה tuma then there's no concern that you would misuse it.
We were assuming why do you bury it? Because you can't derive
benefit from a בכור. bechor. So
it's a dead בכור bechor don't derive benefit from it. But if
we're saying it's like it's not there and it doesn't cause טומאה
tumah, so why do you have to bury it? Okay.
Use it as a fertilizer, don't bury it.
I mean so you can derive benefit. But for the same by
virtue of the same argument that it's not present to cause טומאה
tumah, it's not present to be. for the same by the same
argument that if it's not present to cause טומאה, tumah it's not
present to be forbidden in benefit. Whatever makes it considered not present,
so if it doesn't cause טומאה, tumah then if there's nothing there
to be forbidden in benefit, so why are you burying it?
כדי לפרסם Kedei lefarsem שהיא פטור מן הבכורה. shehee patur min habechora.
You're right, we're really not afraid you're going to misuse it. But
if you don't do a little burial, people will say, "Oh, that
didn't count. The animal was a miscarriage, they just threw it out,
whatever, they used it for fertilizer, whatever, it didn't count." And therefore
the next child you'll say is a בכור bechor by the cow.
If you bury it, it's making a statement. We treat this as
a birth, and we're burying it, and therefore we're treating it as
a בכור. bechor. You don't really have to, and therefore you'll know
that the second child is not a בכור. bechor. Now what do
we see? אמר ולד מעליהו. Amar velad ma'aleihu. So you see that
the animal is considered to have given- it's a fetus in the
sense that the mother has given birth and the next child is
not a בכור. bechor. So if that's true, that the next child
is not a בכור, bechor, דמאי טעמא רבי שמעון מטמא לא במגע
ולא במשא? demai tama Rabbi Shimon metamei lo bemaga velo bemassa? Let's
make sense of this. You have this irony. The mother is considered
to have given birth, but there's no child, there's nothing that she
gave birth to. So how do you explain that?
So ענה רבי יוחנן, ana Rabbi Yochanan, so came along the same
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. who is explaining רבי שמעון, and רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan. said, אמר רבי יוחנן משום ביטול ברוב נהגו בו. Amar
Rabbi Yochanan mishum bittul berov nahagu bo. Yes, of course there was
a fetus there, it wasn't that there was no fetus, but the
fetus lost its status because of all the other stuff that was
there. It negated it by the majority. It wasn't just the fetus,
and therefore it lost its status. So this is actually quite interesting,
which is nicely brought out by this גמרא, this sort of irony
or the bizarre idea here that you have a woman or a
cow in this case giving birth and their status is having טומאה
of a childbirth or in the cow's case is a case about
פטר רחם, peter rechem, the next one is not a בכור, bechor,
but you actually look at the thing that came out and you
say, "Oh, that doesn't have a status of a fetus." They gave
birth, but there was a fetus but it got negated, it lost
its identity. So actually the person has given birth but the thing
is not a fetus.
אמר רבי אמי אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan.
So now back to רבי יוחנן. Rebbe Yochanan ומודי רבי שמעון, Umodei
Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון admits, oh that was exactly what I was
saying because that was implicit in our משנה, mishna, שאמו טמאה לידה,
she'imo tmeia leida, that the mother, although the fetus is not considered
present, the mother still has given birth. And the same in the
משנה mishna by the case about the בכור, bechor, that the next
child is not considered a בכור. bechor. Or the next calf in
the case of the cow. אמר הוא סבר ליה רבי אמי. Amar
hu savar lei Rabbi Ami. So a certain elder said to רבי
אמי, Rabbi Ami, אפרי לך טעמיה דרבי יוחנן. Aprei lach tameih deRabbi
Yochanan. Let me explain to you the reason of רבי יוחנן. Rebbe
Yochanan דאמר קרא אשה כי תזריע וילדה זכר. De'amar kra isha ki
tazria veyalda zachar. If a woman gives forth seed and gives birth
to a boy, a
male. He's understanding that why is this considered a birth? אפילו לא
ילדה אלא כעין שהזריע טמאה לידה. Afilu lo yalda ela ke'ein shehizria
tmeia leida. That even if what comes out is only like what
went in, or only like the seed that she admits, meaning if
it's basically liquefied, nevertheless she is טמאה לידה. tmeia leida. So therefore,
although it is liquefied, it's like זרע, zera, nevertheless because it had
been a fetus but it did liquefy, her status is that still
of טמאה לידה, tmeia leida, which again raises the question: when did
it liquefy? When it was in her womb, after it came out?
It seems to be saying even in her womb. Even if it's
turned to liquid in her womb, because it had been a fetus,
even if it's in this state right now, she is טמאה לידה,
tmeia leida, even though it does not have that status for the
fetus itself. ריש לקיש אמר. Resh Lakish amar. Now, ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish said, we have now been focusing on majority and simple laws
of רוב. rov. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish has a similar approach why
according to רבי שמעון it doesn't have the status, but not because
of רוב. rov. Right? Again, remember, רבי שמעון is just a דעת
יחיד. da'at yachid. According to the חכמים, you know, this fetus, dissolved
fetus is a fetus for the טומאה of the house and so
on. But within רבי שמעון, the reason we've given is
majority of other liquids. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said a different reason
which brings us back to the issue of appearances that we discussed
before. ריש לקיש אמר שפיר שטרפוהו במימיו. Resh Lakish amar shapir shetarfuhu
bemaymav. This type of a fetus that was sort
of scrambled with its waters, with its embryonic liquid, נעשה כמת שנתבלבלה
צורתו. na'asa kemet shenitbalbela tzurato.
It is like a corpse that the appearance has been completely effaced,
has been mixed up. So he's basically saying it's not because of
majority, it's when it stops looking like a fetus and particularly when
the facial features have been completely sort of destroyed, then it loses
its status. So that is again- now again, remember, if you had
a real corpse and you had a chunk of flesh, a כזית
of flesh, you don't need facial features, you have a כזית of
flesh. But this goes back to Tosafot's idea that this is not-
doesn't have flesh, doesn't have bones, it just has the idea of
a whole מת. So he says it cannot be considered a whole
מת if it loses its facial features and it loses its appearance,
and it's not because of majority. That actually is more intuitively, I
would say, what you would say by רבי שמעון. You know why
if it's dissolved it's not a מת? Because there's nothing here that
looks like a מת, right? It's not because of some technical 51
percent רוב rov idea, but it loses all appearance. And that's what
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says. So let's just read one more line
about this, what
which would nothing to do...
Yeah, because this is much more extreme than that.
אמר ליה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש: Amar leh Rebbe Yochanan leh Resh
Lakish: מת שנשתבשו צורותיו מנלן דטהור? Meys shenishtabshu tzurasov minhalan detahor? So
רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan said to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, because רבי
יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan said it was רוב. rov. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
introduced this idea that it's that it lost its appearance. So where
do you know that it's טהור? אילימא מהא דאמר רב שבתאי אמר
רבי יצחק מגדלאה, Ileima meha deamar Rav Shabtai amar Rebbe Yitzchak Magdala,
if it's because of רב שבתאי Rav Shabtai said in the name
of רבי יצחק מגדלאה, Rebbe Yitzchak Magdala, interesting name. ואמרי לה אמר
רבי יצחק מגדלאה אמר רב שבתאי, Ve'amri lah amar Rebbe Yitzchak Magdala
amar Rav Shabtai, some say it was the reverse. מת שנשרף ושלדו
קיימת טמא. Meys shenisraf veshildu kayemes tamey. I know, I was thinking
about the same thing but I wasn't going to say it. מת
שנשרף ושלדו קיימת טמא, Meys shenisraf veshildu kayemes tamey, that if a
מת was burnt and its form was present, either that means it
was charred but it still had its basic body shape or we're
going to see it was let's say on a table and you
had the dirt but you had the ashes but the ashes still
were the
outline, then we're going to end here because it's too big to
finish. But anyway we are now going to continue tomorrow by this
question. רבי יוחנן says it loses its status because of רוב, rov,
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says it loses its status because it lost
its form, and we're going to see רבי יוחנן and ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish debating this issue whether form matters as we wrap this
up tomorrow.